Dear Headmistress,
mắt kính thưa cô chủ nhiệm là em nhóm
my group consists of people working in companies and
chúng em người thì làm công ty người làm
going to the market, all very busy. Even at home, we're
đi chợ rất là bận rộn ra đình lào cũng
very busy. Sometimes, when we
rất là bận rộn mà có lúc chúng em mà
want to join the Dharma assembly, go to the market, or hold a
muốn họ Đạo tràng này và đi chợ Duyên đi
ceremony, it's very difficult to call each other. There
khai đàn các thứ gọi nhau rất là khó rất
are many reasons why we feel very
là nhiều lý do chúng con cũng thấy rất
stuck here.
là bế tắc ở chỗ này đấy ạ Cái Kính thưa
Dear fellow practitioners, there's nothing wrong with this.
quý đạo hữu cái chỗ này thì không có gì
First, like little
về tác cả đâu ạ Đầu tiên mặc cái đứa bé
Long learning to walk, he falls down and up,
Long mới tập đi thì nó ngã lên ngã xuống
right? Then he learns to walk, takes
đúng không Thế rồi nó đi được thì nó đi
a few steps, then he knows how to walk, and now he's good at
vài bước như sau nó biết đi giờ giỏi rồi
running. At first, everyone doesn't understand
lo chạy mới đầu mọi người chưa hiểu được
the meaning of practice, they're not used to it, so it's slow,
cái ý nghĩa của việc tu tập chưa quen
it's difficult, and requires
được thì nó sẽ trễ này nó sẽ khó và cần
encouragement. Later, everyone understands the meaning of practice and becomes very diligent. At
sách tấn sau này mọi người hiểu được ý
that time, they even compete for
nghĩa tu tập thì chăm lắm lúc bấy giờ
tasks. Initially, the mind focused on cultivating the mind,
còn tranh nhau việc đấy mới đầu tâm
establishing Dharma assemblies. At
chiếu Hoàn quán lập ra các đạo tràng tử
first, there were only 23 people, and they encouraged each other
tâm thế mới đầu chỉ có 23 người sách tấn
little by little.
từng chút một thế
In class, it became a daily routine, and
ở lớp nó trở thành cái món ăn hàng ngày
people called it "what is there to do, what is there to do,
rồi người ta gọi là có việc gì không có
what is there not to do," and
việc gì không có việc gì không mà người
they arranged for everyone to do housework.  Joining in and
ta bố trí ngoan toàn việc nhà vào với
doing work is because the people
lại việc công việc được bởi vì đạo trang
in that group are also Vietnamese, they
của trên đấy cũng là người Việt Nam cũng
have husbands and wives, they have the
có chồng cũng có vợ cũng có môi trường
same living environment, they do the same business. If
sống như thế cũng làm ăn như thế Bật tất
we are all like that, then what the previous
cả chúng ta đều như thế thì người trước
generation could arrange, the next generation can also arrange. It's not like some
người ta bố trí được người sau sẽ bố trí
groups are full of
được chứ có phải là đạo tràng ngày toàn
unemployed people, or some are full of
rồi đi làm đạo chẳng kia toàn người thất
people with
nghiệp đâu hay đạo tràng này là người có
families, or some are full of
gia đình Một đạo tràng kia toàn những
people who are single and lonely. It's not like
người gọi là không gia đình ế ẩm đâu
everyone in the world has a
phải anh cứ đời Hữu trên ai cũng có gia
family, children, grandchildren, and a job;
đình cũng có con cháu cũng có công việc
no one is without one. It's just that the level of
không ai là không cả Chỉ có điều là mức
enlightenment is different, and so is the level of diligence.
độ giác ngộ khác nhau thì tinh tấn khác
That's the right path, isn't it? To
nhau Nó quỹ đạo hữu thấy đúng không mức
achieve enlightenment,
độ giác ngộ thì muốn cho giác ngộ được
you need to create information groups with
thì các bạn phải lập các ban thông tin
lots of Dharma teachings in chat groups, and then
đầy các bài pháp vào ở các nhóm chat rồi
divide the groups into smaller ones.
chia nhỏ nhóm ra nhá
For example, within a 10km radius, there
cho ví dụ như thế này trong vòng 10km
are eight people, so we can
này thì có tám người thì chúng ta lại
divide them into 5km with four or
chia tiếp ra thành 5km có bốn người hoặc
three people. They will work together,
ba người đấy người ta sẽ cùng với nhau
so when someone needs help at home, there's
thế thì khi nhà người ta có việc thấy
someone to assist.  For example,
người ta cần có một người giúp đỡ ví dụ
within a 4km radius, there's a helper, and
trong 4km lại có một người người ta lại
neighbors who can help.
có hàng xóm có việc giúp đỡ Thế thì ba
These three people need to come and help. When they
cái người này phải đến giúp giúp thì
ask for help, I'll guide
người ta sẽ hỏi mình mình sẽ hướng dẫn
them on how to come and help.
cho người ta cái cách người ta đến rút
It's not yet perfect. The important thing
thế nào nhé Nó chưa lên là Cái quan
is that, firstly, we
trọng là các bạn này thứ nhất này Cùng
learn about the temple bells and gongs online, we buy them online, we
nhau học chuông mõ qua mạng mua cho ngõ
have to learn online. Secondly, we
phải học qua mạng thứ hai là cùng nhau
learn about the rituals and ceremonies, and
học cái bạch lễ làm làm các đám lễ mà
we have to do all the things related to funerals and memorial services.
giỗ lễ tất cả các thứ là mình phải làm
Thirdly, the main knowledge is that
thứ ba là kiến thức chủ yếu là cái cái
this committee transmits all the
ban cán sự này là truyền tất cả các
updated information and knowledge from the temple and the
thông tin kiến thức cập nhật từ chùa Từ
club down to each member. They
câu lạc bộ xuống cho từng thành viên một
will update themselves, and that's how it
thì người ta sẽ sẽ cập nhật thì thôi mới
will gradually develop. There's no need to
lạ
rush. I like to see things go smoothly and completely. If
vội nhé Mình thích tinh tan hết vỡ của
anyone needs help, I'll help them. Essentially, it's
mình là được Ai có việc gì mình giúp đỡ
like
được cho ngày ra thực chất ra như thế
this: the foundation of the Buddhist community. For example, I
này là các quỹ đạo hữu ạ
have a family that's suffering from karma. Someone is sick, they're in
em có một nhà người ta bị nghiệp chẳng ạ
pain, and a
Cái người ốm bệnh người ta đang đau mà
Buddhist follower comes to chant scriptures for 2 or 3 days and sees that the
hay phật tử Đến tụng kinh 2 3 ngày thấy
pain subsides. That's what I like. Not necessarily, not yet. So, it just continues...
ta đỡ đau thế là Ham Chưa hẳn chưa Hàm
Inviting more people in makes it
Thế là cứ rủ thêm người vào thế là càng
faster and faster as you see them getting better.
ngày thấy người ta đỡ bệnh thì càng
Or, in this house, my child is depressed, and to
nhanh hoặc nhà này con tao bị trầm cả
be honest,
mình đi thật ra mà nói là nó đang chửi
they're cursing and attacking me. I gather around a
bới nó đang đánh mình đến mình tụ khoảng
month and see the child getting better. So, no matter how difficult you are, you must be diligent. If there's
lừa tháng thấy con người ta đỡ Thế là
benefit, there will be
ta gọi là có lợi ích thì sẽ có tinh tấn
diligence. Above all, the tree will thrive. Rest assured, it will develop. I beg you, I ask for
nhá trên là cây Yên tâm sẽ phát triển
your guidance. And remember, as Dharma center leaders, we must review all information and continuously update it for our Dharma center. If we don't do that, we won't be able to promote the Dharma. If we can't do it, the Dharma will leave.
làm được đó thì đạo chào mình sẽ rời giả
But we also keep people updated with
còn hai lao người ta cũng được cập nhật
new information. For example,
thông tin mới ví dụ như là những cái
information for this Dharma center... (this is just
thông tin để đạo tràng này ví dụ từ đây
an example). If the Dharma center sees this Dharma center's
là nói một ví dụ thôi đạo thấy đạo tràng
progress, we should share it with
này
all the Buddhists, right? All the
cả các phật tử đúng không tất cả các
programs for career transformation, we should share
chương trình chuyển nghiệp mình đưa
information about all the practice programs, we should share information about
mình đưa thông tin mình đưa nhiều về từ
natural motivation. The
tự nhiên sách tấn được mọi người thôi
only problem is that if the information just keeps flowing, the
Chỉ có điều là thông tin chỉ chạy thì
Dharma center will...  If things don't develop, but
đạo tràng sẽ không phát triển được còn
the information is good, then the community will
thông tin mà tốt thì đạo tràng sẽ phát
develop well and have a foundation of spiritual practice, okay? Yes,
triển tốt có quỹ đạo hữu nhé à
yes.
ừ ừ